<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-29T14:42:56-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Two minute spates</title><subtitle>Entrepreneurship and software development in Ruby, Rails, javascript, Clojure, Go, Objective-C, iOS. Some other life stuff too.</subtitle><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Last night I had a dream</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/10/last-night-i-had-a-dream/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Last night I had a dream" /><published>2017-01-10T07:39:52-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-10T07:39:52-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/10/last-night-i-had-a-dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/10/last-night-i-had-a-dream/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit: I wrote this back in November of 2016. Two days ago, 2016-01-08, my paternal grandfather, John Smietana, also passed. It is hard to keep up.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I had a dream. I dreamt of a woman so strong that she let love conquer death just to console her grandson. In my dream, she had yet to realize she had passed over to the other side and worried about giving me hugs and comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/67828440@N05/31386343584/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;memaw-and-myself&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/683/31386343584_0e66f5e7c9_n.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; alt=&quot;memaw-and-myself&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a year and two days ago that my grandmother, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legacy.com/obituaries/onlineathens/obituary.aspx?pid=176638501&quot;&gt;Memaw Crumbley* nee Callie Ann Price, passed away&lt;/a&gt;. I know exactly where I was when it happened. I was sitting in a meeting room at Peachtree Medical Billing. My mom texted me to let me know that it wouldn’t be long. I left as soon as I could and made it to her house about twenty minutes after she passed. I tell you this not for you but for me. This isn’t the important part. This is the cathartic get-it-out part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jonathanrwallace.com/blog/2015/09/11/my-first-eulogy/&quot;&gt;Over a year ago, I wrote a eulogy for my grandfather who meant a great deal to me.&lt;/a&gt; I don’t remember how difficult it was to write the eulogy for Grandaddy now but it seems easy in comparison. I was able to write it within the first month of his passing. The words came easier somehow**.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared with a friend that just this past month I finally had the right words to begin working on my eulogy for Memaw. She expressed confusion as I hadn’t shared any news of anyone passing recently. It has taken me over a year to find the thoughts that feel right to me. Hopefully, they translate into words and resonate with you too, dear reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s fascinates me. When my family first moved to Georgia, we did so to move in and take care of my great-grandmother, Thelma Crumbley, my grandfather Jim’s mother. She was in the earlier to mid-stages of the disease and we lived with her for approximately seventeen months. Ever since then, I’ve found myself focused on the concept of identity. When a physical disorder leads to the erosion of the self, what is a person? I often consider the physical processes that lead to the social and cultural manifestations of personality and identity.  How does our consciousness interpret adrenaline? How does our consciousness interpret oxytocin? When we have the DSM-V, how much of that is due to interpretation versus physical processes that are no longer in balance? Are the physical processes a one way function that crosses a threshold never to return?  What is a person again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t had any answers to that question over the years but I think I’m closer to having one now. And I do find it interesting that for years I’ve considered &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jonathanrwallace.com/blog/2016/11/13/resonating-principles/&quot;&gt;integrity to be my most important principle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good friend of mine reminded me of a moment we shared in college. We were walking in downtown Athens and I asked him if he had a favorite word. At the time he didn’t but it was a memory that stuck with him over the years. I’m happy he reminded me of that moment.  At the time, I shared my favorite word and I bet you can guess what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day in the last few days Grandaddy’s life, I took it upon myself to distract Memaw from the pain and distress Grandaddy was in evidenced by his loud, labored breathing. We cuddled on her bed spending a few hours looking at pictures and took a couple of short walks to the end of the driveway. She didn’t remember my name or who I was but she still enjoyed spending time with me. When I broke down in tears of grief, she still had the strength and compassion to comfort me. Her verbal communication was essentially non-existent but for one brief moment she sang a portion of bee-ay-bay on the front porch to Charlie who wondered about obliviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re coming up on one of my most favorite times of the year, the winter holidays. November and December feel so special to me in large part to the warm, caring memories that Memaw engendered. She spent a great deal of time decorating and making her house extra cozy for both Thanksgiving and Christmas.  She spent months crafting and creating the loving experience that I seek to emulate at this time of the year (even though I fall miles short).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*. My opinion is that Me-maw is the inversion of maw-me or mommy. I’m pretty sure that’s the first word everyone was trying to teach me and I’ve always had challenges where I want to mix up the order of syllables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**. After rereading &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jonathanrwallace.com/blog/2015/09/11/my-first-eulogy/&quot;&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, I now know that part of the reason that I couldn’t write as quickly and easily for Memaw is that she suffered from Alzheimer’s for many years which degraded my memories of our interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the last picture I took of Memaw after Grandaddy’s memorial service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/67828440@N05/21314719794/in/datetaken/&quot; title=&quot;Untitled&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5669/21314719794_27e5db7be5_n.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; alt=&quot;Untitled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="eulogy" /><summary type="html">Edit: I wrote this back in November of 2016. Two days ago, 2016-01-08, my paternal grandfather, John Smietana, also passed. It is hard to keep up. Last night, I had a dream. I dreamt of a woman so strong that she let love conquer death just to console her grandson. In my dream, she had yet to realize she had passed over to the other side and worried about giving me hugs and comfort. It was a year and two days ago that my grandmother, Memaw Crumbley* nee Callie Ann Price, passed away. I know exactly where I was when it happened. I was sitting in a meeting room at Peachtree Medical Billing. My mom texted me to let me know that it wouldn’t be long. I left as soon as I could and made it to her house about twenty minutes after she passed. I tell you this not for you but for me. This isn’t the important part. This is the cathartic get-it-out part. Over a year ago, I wrote a eulogy for my grandfather who meant a great deal to me. I don’t remember how difficult it was to write the eulogy for Grandaddy now but it seems easy in comparison. I was able to write it within the first month of his passing. The words came easier somehow**. I shared with a friend that just this past month I finally had the right words to begin working on my eulogy for Memaw. She expressed confusion as I hadn’t shared any news of anyone passing recently. It has taken me over a year to find the thoughts that feel right to me. Hopefully, they translate into words and resonate with you too, dear reader. Alzheimer’s fascinates me. When my family first moved to Georgia, we did so to move in and take care of my great-grandmother, Thelma Crumbley, my grandfather Jim’s mother. She was in the earlier to mid-stages of the disease and we lived with her for approximately seventeen months. Ever since then, I’ve found myself focused on the concept of identity. When a physical disorder leads to the erosion of the self, what is a person? I often consider the physical processes that lead to the social and cultural manifestations of personality and identity. How does our consciousness interpret adrenaline? How does our consciousness interpret oxytocin? When we have the DSM-V, how much of that is due to interpretation versus physical processes that are no longer in balance? Are the physical processes a one way function that crosses a threshold never to return? What is a person again? I haven’t had any answers to that question over the years but I think I’m closer to having one now. And I do find it interesting that for years I’ve considered integrity to be my most important principle. Another good friend of mine reminded me of a moment we shared in college. We were walking in downtown Athens and I asked him if he had a favorite word. At the time he didn’t but it was a memory that stuck with him over the years. I’m happy he reminded me of that moment. At the time, I shared my favorite word and I bet you can guess what it is. One day in the last few days Grandaddy’s life, I took it upon myself to distract Memaw from the pain and distress Grandaddy was in evidenced by his loud, labored breathing. We cuddled on her bed spending a few hours looking at pictures and took a couple of short walks to the end of the driveway. She didn’t remember my name or who I was but she still enjoyed spending time with me. When I broke down in tears of grief, she still had the strength and compassion to comfort me. Her verbal communication was essentially non-existent but for one brief moment she sang a portion of bee-ay-bay on the front porch to Charlie who wondered about obliviously. We’re coming up on one of my most favorite times of the year, the winter holidays. November and December feel so special to me in large part to the warm, caring memories that Memaw engendered. She spent a great deal of time decorating and making her house extra cozy for both Thanksgiving and Christmas. She spent months crafting and creating the loving experience that I seek to emulate at this time of the year (even though I fall miles short). *. My opinion is that Me-maw is the inversion of maw-me or mommy. I’m pretty sure that’s the first word everyone was trying to teach me and I’ve always had challenges where I want to mix up the order of syllables. **. After rereading that post, I now know that part of the reason that I couldn’t write as quickly and easily for Memaw is that she suffered from Alzheimer’s for many years which degraded my memories of our interactions. Here’s the last picture I took of Memaw after Grandaddy’s memorial service.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">So you want to learn how to program</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/01/so-you-want-to-learn-how-to-program/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="So you want to learn how to program" /><published>2017-01-01T15:40:46-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-01T15:40:46-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/01/so-you-want-to-learn-how-to-program</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2017/01/01/so-you-want-to-learn-how-to-program/">&lt;p&gt;There’s only question that I’ve been asked more than “What do I do to learn how
to program?”&lt;a href=&quot;#question&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt;. I’m pretty certain that the programming focused question will
surpass the current champion sometime in 2017. In this post, I’ll answer how to
learn to program at a high level, follow up with some concrete references for
getting started as well as my roadmap for Ruby and Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/rcpl/3969420357/in/photolist-73Ljo2-nUHdqP-cLQ2pA-rMWtFu-cgwn5-o9zKDL-8JZyip-psr9mZ-5VsNnJ-66DDmf-DHS6Qw-bLJ2ua-bLJ2RH-6WtRoh-fa5NsN-bxPk1u-bLJ2gT-bLLfcn-bLJ1o4-bLJ2rV-bxPknQ-bxPkPQ-bxRpQs-bLLjpr-bxRxHm-bxPjjC-bLJ3EK-bxPje7-bxPkpY-bxRoHL-bLJ3b6-bxPkyq-9yGACj-bLL6ER-bLJ1xD-phfvvL-bLLfa6-bLJ1JT-bLJ1vD-bxRCQJ-bLJ1BR-bLGvA2-bxPkMU-bLJ22X-bLL6MD-bLJ1DP-bxPkw9-8nVeLx-pytkiv-otRtyE&quot; title=&quot;Drop-In Programming&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/3/2492/3969420357_fa85157081.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;333&quot; alt=&quot;Drop-In Programming&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is only one secret to learning software development successfully:
motivation. Stay motivated. If you know why you’re motivated, you’ll be able to
best nurture your interest and desire. Are you learning software development so
that you may edit a webpage? Customize your myspace page? Build a website?  Know
how to speak coherently to your contractors as you spec out your nifty startup?
Script hot keys in your video game? Write a pokebot for facebook? Webscrape
your favorite youtube videos?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an existing end goal in mind, re-visiting it will help when you find
yourself struggling with a new concept or piece of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentors&quot;&gt;Mentors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to help maintain your motivation, and the second most important
thing you can do is to find mentors. You don’t have to have multiple mentors
but find at least one. A good mentor will help you maintain your motivation by
focusing on your successes, acknowledging your struggles, and helping you when
you get stuck on the little things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting stuck on the little things happens all the time to all programmers of
all experience levels. For example, you found a nifty stack overflow solution
and you pasted it in your editor and it doesn’t work. You understand the
solution on stack overflow, it makes sense that it should work but it does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a programmer, I always feel ignorant.  I always feel that there is more to
learn or that something I’m trying to learn seems very difficult. It makes my
brain hurt. That’s normal. Eventually, you have longer and longer stretches of
productivity but those moments of struggle never fail to re-appear. If you can
learn to love the process, you’ll love programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beginners-resources&quot;&gt;Beginners resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For beginners with no experience with software development, &lt;a href=&quot;https://scratch.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;check out scratch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous other resources for getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bandofcoders.com/girlsacademy/&quot;&gt;Band of Coders Girls Academy&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://girlswhocode.com/&quot;&gt;Girls Who Code&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blackgirlscode.com/&quot;&gt;Black Girls Code&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mywit.org/wit-participate/wit-girls/&quot;&gt;WIT Girls&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.100girlsofcode.com/conyers-ga.html&quot;&gt;100 Girls of Code (in Conyers, GA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two links will help you find the nearest support group.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.org/learn/local&quot;&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://coderdojo.com/&quot;&gt;Coder Dojo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some good intro sites.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kids4coding.com&quot;&gt;Kids for Coding&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hourofcode.com/us/learn&quot;&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun ways to learn:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://codecombat.com/&quot;&gt;Code Combat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codewars.com/&quot;&gt;Code Wars&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tomorrowcorporation.com/humanresourcemachine&quot;&gt;Human Resource Machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jessica Dennis, Niya Panamdanam, Jeff Ammons, Liz Ojukwu, marshmallowrobot, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/angelmbanks&quot;&gt;Angel Banks&lt;/a&gt;, and Jennifer Mann for the above suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ruby-and-rails&quot;&gt;Ruby and Rails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for my recommendations for Ruby/Rails, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1. Use virtualbox to set up a ubuntu instance, https://www.virtualbox.org/.

2. Set up rbenv, git, ruby, rails, mysql, and postgresql: https://gorails.com/setup

3. Start on a ruby tutorail: http://ruby.learncodethehardway.org/

4. Do a command line refresher: http://cli.learncodethehardway.org/book/

5. A somewhat simple rails app tutorial: http://guides.railsgirls.com/app/

6. A good comprehensive rails tutorial: http://www.railstutorial.org/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot going on when learning how to develop web apps. If you can
compartmentalize and focus on one or two things at a time, it’ll be much easier
going. Here’s a nice little blog post about all the things that are involved:
https://www.codefellows.org/blogs/this-is-why-learning-rails-is-hard/ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p.s. Don’t burn yourself out attempting too much. Find small wins. Celebrate
your successes.  Do not take mistakes or failure personally. Know that
programming is a continual effort to learn new information on a daily, weekly
and monthly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;question&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt;. “Have you cleaned your room?”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">There’s only question that I’ve been asked more than “What do I do to learn how to program?”*. I’m pretty certain that the programming focused question will surpass the current champion sometime in 2017. In this post, I’ll answer how to learn to program at a high level, follow up with some concrete references for getting started as well as my roadmap for Ruby and Rails. Motivation There is only one secret to learning software development successfully: motivation. Stay motivated. If you know why you’re motivated, you’ll be able to best nurture your interest and desire. Are you learning software development so that you may edit a webpage? Customize your myspace page? Build a website? Know how to speak coherently to your contractors as you spec out your nifty startup? Script hot keys in your video game? Write a pokebot for facebook? Webscrape your favorite youtube videos? If you have an existing end goal in mind, re-visiting it will help when you find yourself struggling with a new concept or piece of technology. Mentors Another way to help maintain your motivation, and the second most important thing you can do is to find mentors. You don’t have to have multiple mentors but find at least one. A good mentor will help you maintain your motivation by focusing on your successes, acknowledging your struggles, and helping you when you get stuck on the little things. Getting stuck on the little things happens all the time to all programmers of all experience levels. For example, you found a nifty stack overflow solution and you pasted it in your editor and it doesn’t work. You understand the solution on stack overflow, it makes sense that it should work but it does not. As a programmer, I always feel ignorant. I always feel that there is more to learn or that something I’m trying to learn seems very difficult. It makes my brain hurt. That’s normal. Eventually, you have longer and longer stretches of productivity but those moments of struggle never fail to re-appear. If you can learn to love the process, you’ll love programming. Beginners resources For beginners with no experience with software development, check out scratch. There are numerous other resources for getting started. Band of Coders Girls Academy Girls Who Code Black Girls Code WIT Girls 100 Girls of Code (in Conyers, GA) These two links will help you find the nearest support group. Code.org Coder Dojo Here are some good intro sites. Kids for Coding Hour of Code Fun ways to learn: Code Combat Code Wars Human Resource Machine Thanks to Jessica Dennis, Niya Panamdanam, Jeff Ammons, Liz Ojukwu, marshmallowrobot, Angel Banks, and Jennifer Mann for the above suggestions. Ruby and Rails If you’re looking for my recommendations for Ruby/Rails, read on. 1. Use virtualbox to set up a ubuntu instance, https://www.virtualbox.org/. 2. Set up rbenv, git, ruby, rails, mysql, and postgresql: https://gorails.com/setup 3. Start on a ruby tutorail: http://ruby.learncodethehardway.org/ 4. Do a command line refresher: http://cli.learncodethehardway.org/book/ 5. A somewhat simple rails app tutorial: http://guides.railsgirls.com/app/ 6. A good comprehensive rails tutorial: http://www.railstutorial.org/ There’s a lot going on when learning how to develop web apps. If you can compartmentalize and focus on one or two things at a time, it’ll be much easier going. Here’s a nice little blog post about all the things that are involved: https://www.codefellows.org/blogs/this-is-why-learning-rails-is-hard/ . p.s. Don’t burn yourself out attempting too much. Find small wins. Celebrate your successes. Do not take mistakes or failure personally. Know that programming is a continual effort to learn new information on a daily, weekly and monthly basis. *. “Have you cleaned your room?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Resonating Principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/11/13/resonating-principles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resonating Principles" /><published>2016-11-13T16:34:36-05:00</published><updated>2016-11-13T16:34:36-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/11/13/resonating-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2016/11/13/resonating-principles/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the great fortune to follow excellent leaders both in my professional and private life. As early as high school, I learned a great deal from coaches and team captains in sports. In following people who inspired me, I’ve stolen liberally wherever and whenever I can. I’m going to share the principles others shared with me that I value in the workplace and that I share with my reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/everyplace/2742146831/in/photolist-5bjdHD-6XWao9-6XWas9-fjPX4o-aznycb-5fRoTa-ipoWr-eg7arn-bD66h8-bChTKt-rn72x9-9ss32L-oBhfRi-5XMCxN-pYs4Xo-paoj6s-5qvCxE-opEDw-6XS9VX-61WvCA-arsS8v-dt1EYo-duxLqN-4Y9KRW-6XWaL1-6XS9NM-qSBeE5-azjTZH-nmi3U1-5QnakJ-7uPymK-ezpDr4-dt1EUE-sm7Rf-5Ag8D4-e1PGFh-6XS9Hx-dnpvTX-7cboME-4vad4D-dCwA17-ar6EFC-4Y5vLV-dt1EX3-81YMYR-dzbH7A-6moese-azjTkF-7n3Miy-9rQ6LL&quot; title=&quot;Ideal House&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c8.staticflickr.com/3/2295/2742146831_4e2416c31c_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;160&quot; alt=&quot;Ideal House&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my tenure at Highgroove Studios, the inimitable &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seebq.com/&quot;&gt;CBQ&lt;/a&gt;, the CEO and my boss, spent a great deal of time distilling the cultural values that made our consultancy successful.  Those values were being personable, optimistic, and trustworthy and valuing craftsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Highgroove and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bignerdranch.com/&quot;&gt;Big Nerd Ranch&lt;/a&gt; merged, I was invited to be a part of the leadership development team where we discussed our cultural values: being kind, brilliant, and hardworking.  During my time on the leadership development team, we thought long and hard about whether those values still applied to the larger company after the merger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a people manager, I often start the first four or five 1-on-1 meetings by sharing my values with the people that I serve. My goal is to help the people that I serve get to know me more quickly and, hopefully, spark a deeper discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are those values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being personable: I like to work with others that are friendly and empathetic with their co-workers, their users, and their stakeholders. It is through empathy and a sincere value of others that we can determine how to work most effectively with one another.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being optimistic: A belief in self and in others. A belief that big, hairy, audacious goals are achievable. It is tempting to become cynical around computers–why I find this value all the more important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trusting: Assume the best intentions of others and the organization. I’m a fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanlon%27s_razor&quot;&gt;Hanlon’s razor&lt;/a&gt;.  Distrust is an organizational tax that reduces efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;craftspersonship: Understand that software development is ultimately a craft that entails trade-offs both on a technical level and an organizational level. A craftsperson seeks to master all tools and use the correct tool at the correct time to the most effect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integrity: The foundational principle supporting the above. When times are tough, am I operating with integrity? Am I acting in accordance with the values espoused above?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazing things are accomplished when there’s a unity of values and mission. The above values detail how I most enjoy achieving amazing things. What values do you hold dear?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><category term="management" /><category term="principles" /><summary type="html">I’ve had the great fortune to follow excellent leaders both in my professional and private life. As early as high school, I learned a great deal from coaches and team captains in sports. In following people who inspired me, I’ve stolen liberally wherever and whenever I can. I’m going to share the principles others shared with me that I value in the workplace and that I share with my reports. During my tenure at Highgroove Studios, the inimitable CBQ, the CEO and my boss, spent a great deal of time distilling the cultural values that made our consultancy successful. Those values were being personable, optimistic, and trustworthy and valuing craftsmanship. After Highgroove and Big Nerd Ranch merged, I was invited to be a part of the leadership development team where we discussed our cultural values: being kind, brilliant, and hardworking. During my time on the leadership development team, we thought long and hard about whether those values still applied to the larger company after the merger. As a people manager, I often start the first four or five 1-on-1 meetings by sharing my values with the people that I serve. My goal is to help the people that I serve get to know me more quickly and, hopefully, spark a deeper discussion. Here are those values: being personable: I like to work with others that are friendly and empathetic with their co-workers, their users, and their stakeholders. It is through empathy and a sincere value of others that we can determine how to work most effectively with one another. being optimistic: A belief in self and in others. A belief that big, hairy, audacious goals are achievable. It is tempting to become cynical around computers–why I find this value all the more important. trusting: Assume the best intentions of others and the organization. I’m a fan of Hanlon’s razor. Distrust is an organizational tax that reduces efficiency. craftspersonship: Understand that software development is ultimately a craft that entails trade-offs both on a technical level and an organizational level. A craftsperson seeks to master all tools and use the correct tool at the correct time to the most effect. integrity: The foundational principle supporting the above. When times are tough, am I operating with integrity? Am I acting in accordance with the values espoused above? Amazing things are accomplished when there’s a unity of values and mission. The above values detail how I most enjoy achieving amazing things. What values do you hold dear?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Eulogy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/09/11/my-first-eulogy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Eulogy" /><published>2015-09-11T07:55:04-04:00</published><updated>2015-09-11T07:55:04-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/09/11/my-first-eulogy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/09/11/my-first-eulogy/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wanting to write a eulogy for my grandfather since the day of his
death, August 20th, 2015. For some insight into my writing process, I tend to
procrastinate an incredible amount while my conscious mind comes of with bon
mots that “I can’t wait to incorporate into the final product.” Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/67828440@N05/20712358293/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;grandaddy &amp;amp; chloe&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5637/20712358293_1ab495a0d1_n.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; alt=&quot;grandaddy &amp;amp; chloe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this topic, one so deeply personal to me, I find myself overwhelmed by the
tsunami of things that I want to say and what I want to convey. I want to do
honor to him as a person, to what he means to me, and to help me process the
closest death I’ve yet experienced in my thirty-six years on this earth. But in
the interest in preserving as much of my memory of him as I can I’m going to
enumerate everything as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned so much from my grandfather, Jim Bowen Crumbley. I only realized the
depth  of his legacy for me due to the time I’ve spent reflecting at his death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I virtually grew up with my grandparents from birth to age eight years as we
lived a couple of blocks away from each other in New Orleans. My Dad captained a
shrimp boat for a few of those years and any time he was offshore on a two week
expedition, we’d live at my grandparents house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my earliest memories with Grandaddy is being tasked with bringing him his
morning coffee. They lived on MacArthur Boulevard and Memaw would hand me his
coffee cup and I’d stare that thing down as if my life depended upon it. Each
wiggle and perturbation of coffee would slow me down as I tried to gentle the
liquid’s agitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember sleeping with them above / on their pillows. I remember Grandaddy
teaching me to shoot rubber bands. I remember playing on his CB radio. I
remember going to get ice for Memaw and Grandaddy when I stayed in a hotel room
with them at age three or four. I remember sleeping in the floor board of one of
the back passenger seats (and fitting in there) on a trip. I remember sleeping
above the back seat wedged against the back window. I remember Grandaddy, Mama
Price and Memaw encouraging me to throw my comfort blanket in the fire which I
gladly did. Thank goodness Memaw ran and grabbed it out right afterwards as I
was asking for it only a few hours later. During that same visit, I remember
Grandaddy teaching me to climb the pecan tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about the value of hard work and the importance of keeping my
possessions nice as I watched Grandaddy meticulously scrap red mud off his shoes
to keep them nice. I heard about stories like the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that Grandaddy would gladly walk five or six miles to visit friends.
He would lay down on the middle of  Hwy 138 to warm himself up on chilly nights
when walking back home. He once gave directions back to Atlanta to a lost
airplane pilot who landed on Hwy 138. He always knew his directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned what love is from him. There’s many people who’ve helped teach me what
it means to love. To forgive. Every Christmas holiday, the joy Grandaddy exuded
handing out his envelopes full of money to each family remember reminds me how
much I’m going to miss him. The forgiveness in his heart that shown through his
eyes when I fried his computer’s motherboard installing RAM backwards (this was
way after I should’ve known better 😊). The pride in his smile when he shook my
hand on the day of my senior piano recital and slipped me a $50 bill. The
conviction in his words and actions when he taught me these last years of what
“in sickness and in health” actually means standing by his wife of sixty-two
years. The sweet giggle of victory when he beat me at checkers because he had
forgotten the rules of chess. The pure pleasure and sheer fear of speed I
learned while riding with him and from watching him race go-karts. Hearing his
story of middle school shenanigans where the girls convinced him to climb out of
his room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning of segregation and the racial dynamics that existed without question in
his youth blew my educated mind and helped cement my feelings on inequality and
power dynamics and the importance of doing what I can to make a difference and
rectify wrongs. Hearing of his wreck as a thirteen year old while driving around
an older African-American worker. He worked at his Uncle’s grocery store.
Hearing about his youth growing up in Brunswick, Georgia as his mother and
father worked and contributed for the WWII effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eating late night desserts with him and Memaw. Watching him drive a tractor at
breakneck speeds while bush hogging the pasture. Watching him watch the
construction of the go-kart track. Watching him play with my kids and sing him
songs to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His last gift to me is the realization that the joys of life that he’s enabled
via love and support for both me, my parents and my family are what make life
feel too short. There’s another level of gratitude for which I should
continually strive. There’s another level of selflessness that I haven’t even
begun to appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t regret the time spent with my kids, their kids or my family. And they
won’t either. I miss you Grandaddy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/hubnut/album/3532229?color=44bbff&amp;amp;background=000000&amp;amp;slideshow=0&amp;amp;video_title=1&amp;amp;video_byline=1&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/couchmode/album/3532229&quot;&gt;Mobile link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been wanting to write a eulogy for my grandfather since the day of his death, August 20th, 2015. For some insight into my writing process, I tend to procrastinate an incredible amount while my conscious mind comes of with bon mots that “I can’t wait to incorporate into the final product.” Ugh. With this topic, one so deeply personal to me, I find myself overwhelmed by the tsunami of things that I want to say and what I want to convey. I want to do honor to him as a person, to what he means to me, and to help me process the closest death I’ve yet experienced in my thirty-six years on this earth. But in the interest in preserving as much of my memory of him as I can I’m going to enumerate everything as quickly as possible. I learned so much from my grandfather, Jim Bowen Crumbley. I only realized the depth of his legacy for me due to the time I’ve spent reflecting at his death. I virtually grew up with my grandparents from birth to age eight years as we lived a couple of blocks away from each other in New Orleans. My Dad captained a shrimp boat for a few of those years and any time he was offshore on a two week expedition, we’d live at my grandparents house. One of my earliest memories with Grandaddy is being tasked with bringing him his morning coffee. They lived on MacArthur Boulevard and Memaw would hand me his coffee cup and I’d stare that thing down as if my life depended upon it. Each wiggle and perturbation of coffee would slow me down as I tried to gentle the liquid’s agitation. I remember sleeping with them above / on their pillows. I remember Grandaddy teaching me to shoot rubber bands. I remember playing on his CB radio. I remember going to get ice for Memaw and Grandaddy when I stayed in a hotel room with them at age three or four. I remember sleeping in the floor board of one of the back passenger seats (and fitting in there) on a trip. I remember sleeping above the back seat wedged against the back window. I remember Grandaddy, Mama Price and Memaw encouraging me to throw my comfort blanket in the fire which I gladly did. Thank goodness Memaw ran and grabbed it out right afterwards as I was asking for it only a few hours later. During that same visit, I remember Grandaddy teaching me to climb the pecan tree. I learned about the value of hard work and the importance of keeping my possessions nice as I watched Grandaddy meticulously scrap red mud off his shoes to keep them nice. I heard about stories like the following. I learned that Grandaddy would gladly walk five or six miles to visit friends. He would lay down on the middle of Hwy 138 to warm himself up on chilly nights when walking back home. He once gave directions back to Atlanta to a lost airplane pilot who landed on Hwy 138. He always knew his directions. I learned what love is from him. There’s many people who’ve helped teach me what it means to love. To forgive. Every Christmas holiday, the joy Grandaddy exuded handing out his envelopes full of money to each family remember reminds me how much I’m going to miss him. The forgiveness in his heart that shown through his eyes when I fried his computer’s motherboard installing RAM backwards (this was way after I should’ve known better 😊). The pride in his smile when he shook my hand on the day of my senior piano recital and slipped me a $50 bill. The conviction in his words and actions when he taught me these last years of what “in sickness and in health” actually means standing by his wife of sixty-two years. The sweet giggle of victory when he beat me at checkers because he had forgotten the rules of chess. The pure pleasure and sheer fear of speed I learned while riding with him and from watching him race go-karts. Hearing his story of middle school shenanigans where the girls convinced him to climb out of his room. Learning of segregation and the racial dynamics that existed without question in his youth blew my educated mind and helped cement my feelings on inequality and power dynamics and the importance of doing what I can to make a difference and rectify wrongs. Hearing of his wreck as a thirteen year old while driving around an older African-American worker. He worked at his Uncle’s grocery store. Hearing about his youth growing up in Brunswick, Georgia as his mother and father worked and contributed for the WWII effort. Eating late night desserts with him and Memaw. Watching him drive a tractor at breakneck speeds while bush hogging the pasture. Watching him watch the construction of the go-kart track. Watching him play with my kids and sing him songs to them. His last gift to me is the realization that the joys of life that he’s enabled via love and support for both me, my parents and my family are what make life feel too short. There’s another level of gratitude for which I should continually strive. There’s another level of selflessness that I haven’t even begun to appreciate. I won’t regret the time spent with my kids, their kids or my family. And they won’t either. I miss you Grandaddy. Mobile link</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">#talkpay</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/05/01/number-talkpay/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="#talkpay" /><published>2015-05-01T21:31:01-04:00</published><updated>2015-05-01T21:31:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/05/01/number-talkpay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/05/01/number-talkpay/">&lt;p&gt;Today, May 1st, International Workers’ Day, twitter has been alive with chat of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/talkpay&quot;&gt;#talkpay&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://modelviewculture.com/news/lets-talk-about-pay&quot;&gt;An
article&lt;/a&gt; in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://modelviewculture.com&quot;&gt;ModelViewCulture&lt;/a&gt; requests that we share our
current salary, title and experience to combat systemic pay inequality. Though I
don’t agree with everything in the article, I’m choosing to take part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/76657755@N04/7408506410&quot; title=&quot;Money by Tax Credits, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7114/7408506410_715acb5f6f_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;160&quot; alt=&quot;Money&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a huge social taboo against sharing salary here in the U.S. The topic of
complete salary transparency has been a topic that I’ve been discussing with
friends and coworkers for many years so I approach it with a great amount of
trepidation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fear violating the social mores and the possible consequences. I
fear revealing competitive information about my company’s business model. I fear
the power of other individuals interpreting my experiences and the arbitrary
values that others place on me in a non-flattering light. I fear alienating
co-workers. I fear alienating future co-workers. I also fear the
reductionist aspect of a title and two numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been someone that chases the highest paying job. I’ve always been
keen on having autonomy and respect. I’ve placed a premium of not having to
drive. I’ve placed a premium on being at home with my children. I’ve placed a
premium on working with kind, collaborative people. To share just the number
betrays the values that I hold dearest. A number doesn’t focus on what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I can’t leave it at a title.  I can’t just leave it at two numbers. I have to
tell the story. The reason to share this information publicly is to humanize the
gap. We already have the numbers that prove there’s a gap in aggregate. Let me
share my story so you know how and why I made the decisions I did and I hope you
may find something of value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power isn’t in the numbers. It is in using the numbers effectively. It is in
knowing your
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_alternative_to_a_negotiated_agreement&quot;&gt;BATNA&lt;/a&gt;
and anticipating theirs. My biggest hope is that these numbers inspire or help
you in some way that I can’t anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my income to the best of my memory not adjusted for inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1997 - 1998 Failed Consultant. I had to return the $600 I was paid because I never delivered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1999 - 2001 Intern. $18/hr no professional software experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2002 - 2004 Graduate Assistant. I don’t remember what I was paid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2005 - 2006 I started working as the IT Manager for a restaurant chain
for ~$30,000. I was told that in 10 years I could probably be making $50,000.
When I received a raise of 10% after working over 100 hours in one week that
year in addition to traveling a good amount of the time, I knew that I’d have
to move on. Note, I managed computers and software, not people, despite the
“Manager” in the title. Fifteen days of PTO a year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2006 - 2007 IT Project Manager. Again, I had no direct reports. I worked here
for a year and a day and was paid $55,000 with a ~$5,000 bonus. One week of
PTO the first year (but you couldn’t use them until the end of the first
year) and two weeks every year thereafter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2007 - 2010 Web Developer. My first full time Ruby on Rails position.
~$60,000 and finished at ~$70,000. This was my first full time remote
position. I valued full time remote at a $30K-$40 premium. I believe I had 15
PTO days per year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2010 - 2015 Web Developer and Technologist to Backend Web Team Manager (with actual
reports). $60K - $118K. This is my current position. I can’t speak highly
enough of all the things that are not covered by those numbers. The people.
The faith, autonomy and trust the company places in their co-workers.  The
quality of the environment due to my coworkers. The “unlimited vacation” due
to &lt;a href=&quot;http://gorowe.com/&quot;&gt;ROWE&lt;/a&gt;. The experiments we tried (including ROWE). The
diversity of backgrounds and experience while sharing the same desire for
self-improvement in a collaborative environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s not covered above? All the concurrent moonlighting I’ve done from 2007
and continue to do now. Starting a local software developer meetup. Continual
mentoring that’s fostered my personal and professional growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family support in all directions allowing me to focus on my career. Societal
norms and privileges not granted to others. Luck. Fortune. Blessings.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">Today, May 1st, International Workers’ Day, twitter has been alive with chat of #talkpay. An article in ModelViewCulture requests that we share our current salary, title and experience to combat systemic pay inequality. Though I don’t agree with everything in the article, I’m choosing to take part. There’s a huge social taboo against sharing salary here in the U.S. The topic of complete salary transparency has been a topic that I’ve been discussing with friends and coworkers for many years so I approach it with a great amount of trepidation. I fear violating the social mores and the possible consequences. I fear revealing competitive information about my company’s business model. I fear the power of other individuals interpreting my experiences and the arbitrary values that others place on me in a non-flattering light. I fear alienating co-workers. I fear alienating future co-workers. I also fear the reductionist aspect of a title and two numbers. I’ve never been someone that chases the highest paying job. I’ve always been keen on having autonomy and respect. I’ve placed a premium of not having to drive. I’ve placed a premium on being at home with my children. I’ve placed a premium on working with kind, collaborative people. To share just the number betrays the values that I hold dearest. A number doesn’t focus on what matters. So I can’t leave it at a title. I can’t just leave it at two numbers. I have to tell the story. The reason to share this information publicly is to humanize the gap. We already have the numbers that prove there’s a gap in aggregate. Let me share my story so you know how and why I made the decisions I did and I hope you may find something of value. The power isn’t in the numbers. It is in using the numbers effectively. It is in knowing your BATNA and anticipating theirs. My biggest hope is that these numbers inspire or help you in some way that I can’t anticipate. Here’s my income to the best of my memory not adjusted for inflation. 1997 - 1998 Failed Consultant. I had to return the $600 I was paid because I never delivered. 1999 - 2001 Intern. $18/hr no professional software experience. 2002 - 2004 Graduate Assistant. I don’t remember what I was paid. 2005 - 2006 I started working as the IT Manager for a restaurant chain for ~$30,000. I was told that in 10 years I could probably be making $50,000. When I received a raise of 10% after working over 100 hours in one week that year in addition to traveling a good amount of the time, I knew that I’d have to move on. Note, I managed computers and software, not people, despite the “Manager” in the title. Fifteen days of PTO a year. 2006 - 2007 IT Project Manager. Again, I had no direct reports. I worked here for a year and a day and was paid $55,000 with a ~$5,000 bonus. One week of PTO the first year (but you couldn’t use them until the end of the first year) and two weeks every year thereafter. 2007 - 2010 Web Developer. My first full time Ruby on Rails position. ~$60,000 and finished at ~$70,000. This was my first full time remote position. I valued full time remote at a $30K-$40 premium. I believe I had 15 PTO days per year. 2010 - 2015 Web Developer and Technologist to Backend Web Team Manager (with actual reports). $60K - $118K. This is my current position. I can’t speak highly enough of all the things that are not covered by those numbers. The people. The faith, autonomy and trust the company places in their co-workers. The quality of the environment due to my coworkers. The “unlimited vacation” due to ROWE. The experiments we tried (including ROWE). The diversity of backgrounds and experience while sharing the same desire for self-improvement in a collaborative environment. What’s not covered above? All the concurrent moonlighting I’ve done from 2007 and continue to do now. Starting a local software developer meetup. Continual mentoring that’s fostered my personal and professional growth. Family support in all directions allowing me to focus on my career. Societal norms and privileges not granted to others. Luck. Fortune. Blessings.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my first haskell</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/15/my-first-haskell/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my first haskell" /><published>2014-07-15T15:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-15T15:18:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/15/my-first-haskell</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/15/my-first-haskell/">&lt;p&gt;Last week I shared my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/07/06/my-code-retreat-syllabus/index.html&quot;&gt;secrets to an amazing code retreat&lt;/a&gt;. Since then &lt;a href=&quot;http://bignerdranch.com&quot;&gt;Big Nerd Ranch&lt;/a&gt; held an internal code retreat (thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/srbiv&quot;&gt;Stafford&lt;/a&gt;) and although I was only able to participate for a couple of sessions due to client work, I learned a couple of things and got to play with a new language. Can you guess which one?!? Read on to found out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/rockandracehorses/3783326324&quot; title=&quot;Born To Run! Rachel Alexandra and Calvin Borel win the $1.25 million Haskell Invitational by Sarah K. Andrew, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3110/3783326324_154fe1441d_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;180&quot; alt=&quot;Born To Run! Rachel Alexandra and Calvin Borel win the $1.25 million Haskell Invitational&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I’ve stated many times how valuable I find code retreats to be, I’m still impressed at how I continue to learn at a consistent rate each time I attend or facilitate. Lucky for me, this time I was able to participate which is so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had three experiences that I’d like to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-simpler-equality-in-ruby&quot;&gt;1. “Simpler” equality in Ruby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way way back when, I shared &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bignerdranch.com/blog/lessons-learned-at-global-day-of-coderetreat/&quot;&gt;what I learned at my first code retreat&lt;/a&gt;. Knowing how equality works in Ruby is a little tricky and understanding the importance of the hash and eql methods is key. But you can also get away with using the Comparable module (thanks &lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenharman.net/&quot;&gt;Steven Harman&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/4a0d0f0403a2b85b383f.js?file=point.rb&quot;&gt; &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricky/dirty part here is determining when a point is “less than” another in a two dimensional coordinate plane. In the above code, I’m making an arbitrary distinction, we only look at the x axis, for the -1 and 1 cases as I really only care about equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-challenges-of-tdd-with-full-stack-integration-tests&quot;&gt;2. Challenges of TDD with full stack integration tests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, I only experienced two full sessions. I was interuppted in the third session where we were constrained to using mute ping-pong TDD. But what was interesting is how in the few minutes we did share, I started with a full integration test. This stumped my partner. And to be honest, it was a little unfair as there’s no way he could write a passing test without resorting to some nefarious behaviors. I later found out that we weren’t the only ones who found starting with a high level integration test challenging when we weren’t able to vocally coordinate with our partner. There’s got to be some profound insight related to documentation, abstraction and code rot over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-haskell&quot;&gt;3. Haskell!!!!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, what I’m most excited about is that I was able to pair with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/letsbreelhere&quot;&gt;Bree Stanwyck&lt;/a&gt; and we used Haskell. This was the first time I was exposed to Haskell other than via a presentation and we managed, with tests, to get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/breestanwyck/479faa4a274f7278b5fb&quot;&gt;functioning Haskell GoL implementation&lt;/a&gt; within the session. I was very impressed with Haskell and look forward to exploring it more in the near future. The elegance and simplicity allows the intent of the GoL algorithm to shine through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my next step, I’m planning on working through &lt;a href=&quot;http://learnyouahaskell.com/&quot;&gt;http://learnyouahaskell.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">Last week I shared my secrets to an amazing code retreat. Since then Big Nerd Ranch held an internal code retreat (thanks Stafford) and although I was only able to participate for a couple of sessions due to client work, I learned a couple of things and got to play with a new language. Can you guess which one?!? Read on to found out. Though I’ve stated many times how valuable I find code retreats to be, I’m still impressed at how I continue to learn at a consistent rate each time I attend or facilitate. Lucky for me, this time I was able to participate which is so much fun. I had three experiences that I’d like to share. 1. “Simpler” equality in Ruby Way way back when, I shared what I learned at my first code retreat. Knowing how equality works in Ruby is a little tricky and understanding the importance of the hash and eql methods is key. But you can also get away with using the Comparable module (thanks Steven Harman). The tricky/dirty part here is determining when a point is “less than” another in a two dimensional coordinate plane. In the above code, I’m making an arbitrary distinction, we only look at the x axis, for the -1 and 1 cases as I really only care about equality. 2. Challenges of TDD with full stack integration tests As I mentioned above, I only experienced two full sessions. I was interuppted in the third session where we were constrained to using mute ping-pong TDD. But what was interesting is how in the few minutes we did share, I started with a full integration test. This stumped my partner. And to be honest, it was a little unfair as there’s no way he could write a passing test without resorting to some nefarious behaviors. I later found out that we weren’t the only ones who found starting with a high level integration test challenging when we weren’t able to vocally coordinate with our partner. There’s got to be some profound insight related to documentation, abstraction and code rot over time. 3. Haskell!!!! Finally, what I’m most excited about is that I was able to pair with Bree Stanwyck and we used Haskell. This was the first time I was exposed to Haskell other than via a presentation and we managed, with tests, to get a functioning Haskell GoL implementation within the session. I was very impressed with Haskell and look forward to exploring it more in the near future. The elegance and simplicity allows the intent of the GoL algorithm to shine through. For my next step, I’m planning on working through http://learnyouahaskell.com/.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my code retreat syllabus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/06/my-code-retreat-syllabus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my code retreat syllabus" /><published>2014-07-06T21:39:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-06T21:39:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/06/my-code-retreat-syllabus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/07/06/my-code-retreat-syllabus/">&lt;p&gt;You may have heard about &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2013/07/04/quick-recap/index.html&quot;&gt;my adventures&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/06/12/year-in-review/index.html&quot;&gt;code retreats&lt;/a&gt;. I greatly enjoy facilitating and participating and over the years I’ve come up with a base itinerary. You can find the official structure &lt;a href=&quot;http://coderetreat.org/facilitating/structure-of-a-coderetreat&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is more of my specific predilections. The day won’t follow this exactly and will vary according to skill level and participants interest but read on to see what I enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/auteurdecinema/6157383349&quot; title=&quot;Self-improvement in progress! by Kenneth Law, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6199/6157383349_77ef7d33dd_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; alt=&quot;Self-improvement in progress!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Breakfast (8am) 
 The start of any good day begins with a good breakfast. I open the doors to the location around 8am for the early risers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction (~ 8:30am)
 The first thing I do is introduce myself. Then I’ll
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;talk about the itinerary of the day and the purpose of the code retreat. The importance of coding without pressure and seeking only to practice and improve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Talk about the difference between perfection and reality (the how much we suck gap).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Talk about the 4 rules of simple design.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Passing tests.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Good names (reveal intent).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;DRY - Don’t repeat yourself (not just code but more imporant, concepts).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Small. Methods, classes, parameters lists, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encourage people to pair with others of different skill levels and platforms and the importance of communication and collaboration.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Introduce GoL.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1st session (~ 9am)
 Let people pair up and practice on the problem.
 Review the approaches used.
 Help the group reflect on what was done, why and the limitations of the approaches chosen.
 Remind them of the problem constraints, “infinite grid”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2nd session (~ 10am)
 Ping pong TDD.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3rd session (~ 11am)
 Mute ping pong TDD (remind them to speak only about language details if they don’t know the language they’ve agreed upon, not implementation questions)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lunch break (~ 12pm)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4th session (~ 1:30pm)
 No loops, no if statements (secretly forcing functional programming paradigms and moving away from array based solutions)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At this point, take stock of the groups energy level. Determine by asking them whether they’re up for one or two more sessions. Also by examining the excitement level in the room. If they’re tired and interest is waning, I’ll make the 5th session the last one. No one is at events like this for punishment purposes. :)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For the last session, I encourage people to have the freedom to make their own choices, no constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5th session (~ 2:30pm)
  I often like to pretend that this session has no constriants only to stop them about 15-25 minutes in and add a constraint. Assuming this is the 2nd to last session, the constraint will be add a third state to a cell. You now have live, dying and dead cells. It now takes two ticks for a cell to die but once it starts dying it will die no matter what the generation after the next. While it is alive, it is considered alive for evaluating the state of other neighboring cells.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6th session (~ 3:30pm)
 Pair up with no constraints. About 15-25 minutes in, ask everyone to switch stations/ computers. In other words, you start with your own code base as a pair and finish with someone else’s. It doesn’t matter if you know the language or not, that’s part of the fun. I call these last two sessions consultant sessions as they mimic what happens with a consultant. 5th session is changing requirements. 6th session is rescue code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Closing circle: Here’s where we recap and give everyone a chance to share three things.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What’re you going to do differently going forward?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What most surprised you?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What did you learn?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of other session idea out there too. Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://coderetreat.org/facilitating/activity-catalog&quot;&gt;the code retreat website for more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">You may have heard about my adventures with code retreats. I greatly enjoy facilitating and participating and over the years I’ve come up with a base itinerary. You can find the official structure here. This is more of my specific predilections. The day won’t follow this exactly and will vary according to skill level and participants interest but read on to see what I enjoy. Breakfast (8am) The start of any good day begins with a good breakfast. I open the doors to the location around 8am for the early risers. Introduction (~ 8:30am) The first thing I do is introduce myself. Then I’ll talk about the itinerary of the day and the purpose of the code retreat. The importance of coding without pressure and seeking only to practice and improve. Talk about the difference between perfection and reality (the how much we suck gap). Talk about the 4 rules of simple design. Passing tests. Good names (reveal intent). DRY - Don’t repeat yourself (not just code but more imporant, concepts). Small. Methods, classes, parameters lists, etc. Encourage people to pair with others of different skill levels and platforms and the importance of communication and collaboration. Introduce GoL. 1st session (~ 9am) Let people pair up and practice on the problem. Review the approaches used. Help the group reflect on what was done, why and the limitations of the approaches chosen. Remind them of the problem constraints, “infinite grid”. 2nd session (~ 10am) Ping pong TDD. 3rd session (~ 11am) Mute ping pong TDD (remind them to speak only about language details if they don’t know the language they’ve agreed upon, not implementation questions) Lunch break (~ 12pm) 4th session (~ 1:30pm) No loops, no if statements (secretly forcing functional programming paradigms and moving away from array based solutions) At this point, take stock of the groups energy level. Determine by asking them whether they’re up for one or two more sessions. Also by examining the excitement level in the room. If they’re tired and interest is waning, I’ll make the 5th session the last one. No one is at events like this for punishment purposes. :) For the last session, I encourage people to have the freedom to make their own choices, no constraints. 5th session (~ 2:30pm) I often like to pretend that this session has no constriants only to stop them about 15-25 minutes in and add a constraint. Assuming this is the 2nd to last session, the constraint will be add a third state to a cell. You now have live, dying and dead cells. It now takes two ticks for a cell to die but once it starts dying it will die no matter what the generation after the next. While it is alive, it is considered alive for evaluating the state of other neighboring cells. 6th session (~ 3:30pm) Pair up with no constraints. About 15-25 minutes in, ask everyone to switch stations/ computers. In other words, you start with your own code base as a pair and finish with someone else’s. It doesn’t matter if you know the language or not, that’s part of the fun. I call these last two sessions consultant sessions as they mimic what happens with a consultant. 5th session is changing requirements. 6th session is rescue code. Closing circle: Here’s where we recap and give everyone a chance to share three things. What’re you going to do differently going forward? What most surprised you? What did you learn? There’s lots of other session idea out there too. Check out the code retreat website for more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Year in review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/06/12/year-in-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Year in review" /><published>2014-06-12T09:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-06-12T09:28:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/06/12/year-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/06/12/year-in-review/">&lt;p&gt;Way back in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/01/14/building-cyberdine-systems-with-kids/&quot;&gt;December&lt;/a&gt;, I promised that I would provide a year in review update. Finally, here it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pagedooley/8349362069&quot; title=&quot;Symphony for 2013 by Kevin Dooley, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8518/8349362069_380fe20922_n.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;143&quot; alt=&quot;Symphony for 2013&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good grief, my year in review for 2013 lands halfway into 2014! Don’t they say that you need perspective to properly judge the past?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2013/01/06/athens-developers-rejoice/&quot;&gt;co-founded&lt;/a&gt; and co-ran the &lt;a href=&quot;http://developersofathens.com&quot;&gt;Developers of Athens&lt;/a&gt; group (neé &lt;a href=&quot;http://meetup.com/Greater-Athens-Area-Software-Developers/&quot;&gt;Greater Athens Area Software Developer Group&lt;/a&gt;) for 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/travisdouce&quot;&gt;Travis Douce&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pendragondevelopment.com/&quot;&gt;Jordan Burke&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://glennstovall.com/&quot;&gt;Glenn Stovall&lt;/a&gt; took over as organizers and have been doing wonderful things. One of the other really awesome things is that Jordan met his cofounder at the meetup and started &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.getvitaminc.com/&quot;&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/01/14/building-cyberdine-systems-with-kids/&quot;&gt;4H robotics instructor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I organized and facilitated the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/athens-code-retreat-2013-tickets-3788649954&quot;&gt;2013 Athens Code Retreat&lt;/a&gt; (with a little help from Travis Douce).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/IndianGuru/status/333158779917045760&quot;&gt;RubyConf India&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2013/09/21/good-news-everyone/&quot;&gt;Rubyconf&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bignerdranch.com/&quot;&gt;Big Nerd Ranch&lt;/a&gt; Tech Talk on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/81416284&quot;&gt;effective debugging in ruby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other cool Big Nerd Ranch things that I can talk about include helping out at
three different recruitment fairs, helping out with sales and estimates as a technical contributor, being chosen for the first Leadership Development program and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bignerdranch.com/blog/serving-you-better-a-new-structure-for-our-team/&quot;&gt;helping with our new organizational structure and becoming a backend manager&lt;/a&gt;. This was in addition to launching a huge refactor for some customer work as well as leading other developers on the project and setting up onboarding documentation for the same project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tangentially related, I had a hand in both Travis Douce and Charlie Maffitt coming aboard at Big Nerd Ranch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, my team got &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2013/07/04/quick-recap/&quot;&gt;2nd place at the 2013 Athens Game Jam&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;http://marilynccole.com/nice-job-hero&quot;&gt;Nice Job Hero!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a pretty busy 2013 and I’m definitely feeling that 2014 is stacking up competitively. Great things have already happened that I haven’t even had the time to share yet but SOON(tm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/krupptastic/4738992473&quot; title=&quot;the future soon by k rupp, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4142/4738992473_38ff2f7971.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;395&quot; alt=&quot;the future soon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">Way back in December, I promised that I would provide a year in review update. Finally, here it is. Good grief, my year in review for 2013 lands halfway into 2014! Don’t they say that you need perspective to properly judge the past? I co-founded and co-ran the Developers of Athens group (neé Greater Athens Area Software Developer Group) for 2013. Travis Douce, Jordan Burke and Glenn Stovall took over as organizers and have been doing wonderful things. One of the other really awesome things is that Jordan met his cofounder at the meetup and started Vitamin C. I was a 4H robotics instructor. I organized and facilitated the 2013 Athens Code Retreat (with a little help from Travis Douce). I spoke at RubyConf India, Rubyconf, and a Big Nerd Ranch Tech Talk on effective debugging in ruby. Other cool Big Nerd Ranch things that I can talk about include helping out at three different recruitment fairs, helping out with sales and estimates as a technical contributor, being chosen for the first Leadership Development program and helping with our new organizational structure and becoming a backend manager. This was in addition to launching a huge refactor for some customer work as well as leading other developers on the project and setting up onboarding documentation for the same project. Tangentially related, I had a hand in both Travis Douce and Charlie Maffitt coming aboard at Big Nerd Ranch. And finally, my team got 2nd place at the 2013 Athens Game Jam for Nice Job Hero!. That’s a pretty busy 2013 and I’m definitely feeling that 2014 is stacking up competitively. Great things have already happened that I haven’t even had the time to share yet but SOON(tm).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building cyberdine systems with kids</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/01/14/building-cyberdine-systems-with-kids/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building cyberdine systems with kids" /><published>2014-01-14T21:52:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-14T21:52:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/01/14/building-cyberdine-systems-with-kids</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/01/14/building-cyberdine-systems-with-kids/">&lt;p&gt;Starting last September, I volunteered to teach and to be the robotics lead for
the local 4H extension office. Check out the post inside to see some cool
videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonaparty/6223120971/&quot; title=&quot;T-800 Terminator by Louis K., on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6169/6223120971_34a94e88b6_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;160&quot; alt=&quot;T-800 Terminator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first couple of meetings we worked on building trebuchets which was a lot of
fun. We’ve since started playing with the Lego Mindstorms NXT kits. We have
three of them and the kids need to share but it has been a great deal of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this pair of videos, we have a walking chicken.. sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/81304491&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/81304491&quot;&gt;VIDEO0075.mp4&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working the kinks out, we had a little more success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/84186555&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/84186555&quot;&gt;Walking Chicken&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last one, another group built a grasshoper with a movable, portable power supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/81304487&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/81304487&quot;&gt;VIDEO0074.mp4&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the videos above came from our December meetup. Below are some from our
January meetup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/84188137&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/84188137&quot;&gt;VIDEO0100&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/84188138&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/84188138&quot;&gt;VIDEO0101.mp4&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/84188139&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/84188139&quot;&gt;VIDEO0102.mp4&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/jonathanrwallace&quot;&gt;Jonathan R. Wallace&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chicken and grasshoper are based off the instructions in the excellent book NXT One-Kit
Creatures. Full disclosure, that’s an affiliate link to the book below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004K1EZMY/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004K1EZMY&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=twominspa-20&quot;&gt;NXT One-Kit Creatures : Five Designs for the LEGO MINDSTORMS NXT 1.0 or 2.0 Kit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twominspa-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=B004K1EZMY&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">Starting last September, I volunteered to teach and to be the robotics lead for the local 4H extension office. Check out the post inside to see some cool videos. The first couple of meetings we worked on building trebuchets which was a lot of fun. We’ve since started playing with the Lego Mindstorms NXT kits. We have three of them and the kids need to share but it has been a great deal of fun. In this pair of videos, we have a walking chicken.. sort of. VIDEO0075.mp4 from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. After working the kinks out, we had a little more success. Walking Chicken from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. In the last one, another group built a grasshoper with a movable, portable power supply. VIDEO0074.mp4 from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. All the videos above came from our December meetup. Below are some from our January meetup. VIDEO0100 from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. VIDEO0101.mp4 from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. VIDEO0102.mp4 from Jonathan R. Wallace on Vimeo. The chicken and grasshoper are based off the instructions in the excellent book NXT One-Kit Creatures. Full disclosure, that’s an affiliate link to the book below. NXT One-Kit Creatures : Five Designs for the LEGO MINDSTORMS NXT 1.0 or 2.0 Kit</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Halfway Through</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2013/12/27/halfway-through/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Halfway Through" /><published>2013-12-27T14:41:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-27T14:41:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2013/12/27/halfway-through</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2013/12/27/halfway-through/">&lt;p&gt;We’re halfway through the winter holidays and I’m not even close to halfway through my holiday vacation todo list. &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt; But, there’re good things a brewin’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/amagill/29207183/&quot; title=&quot;Vancouver pan by AMagill, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/22/29207183_29437e18a9_m.jpg&quot; width=&quot;240&quot; height=&quot;75&quot; alt=&quot;Vancouver pan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often despair when I write down all the things that I want to do and must do as the list itself often overwhelms. But now that we’re over the holiday hump and social obligations lighten their hold on my schedule, I’m finding moments here and there where I’m able to reflect over the last year. There’s more than a few things that I’ve done this year of which I’m proud. But, this post is not the post where I discuss those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’m happy to announce that we’re finally headed to Vancouver in February to visit our great friends, the Matheos family. This trip is something Kristina has dreamed about for many years and I’m happy that we’re finally able ot make it happen. We’re billing this as our 10 year anniversary present since May 29, 2014 marks ten years of wedded bliss!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more technical front, I’ve finally bitten the bullet and learned a little about minecraft. For my Christmas gift to Chloe and Callie, I’ve set up a minecraft pocket edition server. This was not as easy as I hoped it would be. It required some time in the IRC channels but I finally stumbled onto the correct sequence of commands to set it up, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/PocketMine/PocketMine-MP/issues/1012#issuecomment-31226235&quot;&gt;https://github.com/PocketMine/PocketMine-MP/issues/1012#issuecomment-31226235&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That todo list is still waiting for me and I hope to knock a few items more off
before returning to work in January including a year-in-review post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jonathan R Wallace</name></author><summary type="html">We’re halfway through the winter holidays and I’m not even close to halfway through my holiday vacation todo list. sigh But, there’re good things a brewin’. I often despair when I write down all the things that I want to do and must do as the list itself often overwhelms. But now that we’re over the holiday hump and social obligations lighten their hold on my schedule, I’m finding moments here and there where I’m able to reflect over the last year. There’s more than a few things that I’ve done this year of which I’m proud. But, this post is not the post where I discuss those things. Instead, I’m happy to announce that we’re finally headed to Vancouver in February to visit our great friends, the Matheos family. This trip is something Kristina has dreamed about for many years and I’m happy that we’re finally able ot make it happen. We’re billing this as our 10 year anniversary present since May 29, 2014 marks ten years of wedded bliss! On a more technical front, I’ve finally bitten the bullet and learned a little about minecraft. For my Christmas gift to Chloe and Callie, I’ve set up a minecraft pocket edition server. This was not as easy as I hoped it would be. It required some time in the IRC channels but I finally stumbled onto the correct sequence of commands to set it up, https://github.com/PocketMine/PocketMine-MP/issues/1012#issuecomment-31226235. That todo list is still waiting for me and I hope to knock a few items more off before returning to work in January including a year-in-review post.</summary></entry></feed>